Finding Aid for French family papers, ca. 1908-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
French family papers circa 1908-1966
French family
1 linear foot
85190 Aa 2
Files of J. Leslie French, Presbyterian clergyman, and first campus minister at the University of Michigan Tappan Hall Presbyterian Association; and papers of his wife, Edna Cumming French, largely concerning her involvement in the Alumnae Council's fundraising for the construction of the Women's League.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. J. Leslie French (donor no. 3488 ); additional materials came from John G. Young (donor no. 6483 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Rev. James Leslie French was born on January 3, 1877 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. He his A.B. degree from the University of Michigan in 1899 and his M.A. degree in 1900 in the field of Hebrew, Philosophy and Ethics. He graduated from Hartford Theological Seminary in 1902 and was ordained at a meeting of the Grand Rapids Presbytery on July 8, 1902 in Westminster Presbyterian Church in Grand Rapids, Michigan. That same year he married Edna F. Cumming of Port Huron, Michigan. He continued his education abroad for three years: at the University of Berlin, the University of Marburg in Germany and the Sorbonne in Paris. He received his Ph.D. from Hartford Theological Seminary in 1905.
From 1905 to 1914, French was a University Pastor for Presbyterian Students at the University of Michigan. During this time he also held an instructorship in the Department of Semitics, teaching Hellenistic Greek and Hebrew, and gave full time to the University in 1913-14 as acting associate professor.
As the first full-time University pastor to students at a state-supported university, French established the Presbyterian Student Center at the University of Michigan under the sponsorship of the Tappan Presbyterian Association in 1905. French was also an early exponent of the ecumenical principle in student work, and was chairman of the committee which called together the first "Inter-denominational Conference of Church and Guild Workers in State Universities," which met in Ann Arbor in March, 1908. Under his direction the first religious census of the University was taken.
From 1914 to 1925, French was the Minister of Religious Education at Collingwood Avenue Presbyterian Church, Toledo, Ohio. During this time he also organized and became pastor of Northminster Presbyterian Church in Toledo and built the church school unit of this new church. In 1928 he was invited as a delegate to a conference at Iowa University at which Catholics, Protestants and Jews were present. It was there that the delegates set up a co-operative basis for organization on all campuses. This meeting was the beginning of what is now the National Conference of Christian and Jews.
During the period 1925 to 1934, French was the University Pastor for Presbyterian students at the University of West Virginia at Morgantown. He was pastor of First Presbyterian Church at Caro, Michigan from 1934 to 1943 when he retired. He died on July 18, 1962.
The French family collection consists primarily of the papers of J. Leslie French with a scattering of other materials of his wife Edna Cumming French. The J. Leslie French materials relate to the period when he was University Pastor for Presbyterian Students at the University of Michigan. The Edna French papers pertain to University of Michigan alumnae activities, notably her involvement in fund raising for the construction of the Women's League building.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Religion.; Women in charitable work--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Women's League.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students.; Spouses of clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Clothing and dress--1921-1930.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); French, J. Leslie (James Leslie), 1877-1962.; Herdman, Nan.; Herdman, William James, 1848-1906.; Osborn, Stellanova, 1894-1988.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Women's League.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
French, Edna Cumming, 1881-; French, J. Leslie (James Leslie), 1877-1962.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical materials
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1908-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918-1926 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - 1930-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1968 (Box 1)
- James Leslie French (1877-1962)
  - Presbyterian Church (largely University of Michigan)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Tappan Presbyterian Association, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation: Protestant Foundation for International Students (Box 1)
    - Westminster House (Box 1)
    - Presbyterian Student Center on Campus 1950 (Box 1)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Other religious activities (largely University of Michigan)
    - Papers re. teaching of religion at other universities (Box 1)
    - Office of Religious Affairs, U-M, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Religious organizations, U-M (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Bible Chair (Box 1)
    - Christian Endeavor Society (Box 1)
    - Student Christian Association (Religious Education Department) (Box 1)
    - Ecumenical Campus Center (Box 1)
    - Chinese Students at Michigan 1911, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
    - "Little Michigan in Arabia" (Box 1)
  - Other interests
    - Phi Chi Delta, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mountain Mining Mission, West Virginia (French Project) (Box 1)
    - Albion College American Assembly February 3-5, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Edna Cumming French (b. 1881)
  - Papers re. women workers (Box 1)
  - "Status of Women in University Life" (Box 1)
  - Alumnae Council (Women's League Fund-raising)
    - Papers 1926-1929, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1926-1929 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous, 3 envelopes (Box 1)
    (Photos and portraits of international students at the University, photographs of the 1946 mortgage burning of First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor, Michigan, and a photograph of the church at its former location at Huron and Division Streets, Ann Arbor; also photos relating to the building of the Women's League at the University of Michigan)